When I popped off, then you go gave me...
So in this video, we're going to be building the Tyro 69 kit.
Now, this will be a beginner's guide into how to build it, solder it, and what are good techniques to use,
and some of the issues you might come up against and how to solve them.
So we're going to do this together as fast, efficient, yet full of detail as possible.
So PCBWay is one of the leading PCB manufacturers that I even use on a daily basis,
not only to do my projects, but also some of the products that I've designed that's currently in the market,
like the Drone Mesh VUSB, and I'm constantly using them for prototyping,
and I'm also using their assembly services, and they also do have flashing services for specific hardware requirements.
So it's a really great place to have your PCB manufactured or prototyped.
All right, so let's talk about some of the tools we're going to need, because we're not going to really need much,
and also some tools I'd highly recommend, which have dropped in price pretty insane.
So this right here is a soldering iron. This is a portable soldering iron.
This thing used to go for $80, $90. That's when I got mine, and right now it's like $40 or $50.
This is the thing that I carry with me to the field always.
I replaced big motors, big XC60, and I'd highly recommend this little tool, and it can run as your main driver.
I've had this running as my main driver before, because it is just a well-built beast, and anybody would tell you that.
So for this build, we're actually going to be using this to show you how good it actually is,
and we're using this flat tip that it comes with. This will be really good, especially for this small stuff right here.
Also, something that's not included in the kit is the tools.
I do highly recommend this tool right here. I've been using it for quite a while.
You'll probably see it in a couple of my videos.
If you are thinking of getting into drones, this is a must-have tool, because this is titanium-coated,
and these are hex drivers, and every single size you're going to need, which is 1.5mm all the way up to 3mm.
Usually, all micros are 1.5mm, and that's the only thing we're going to be using for this whole build.
So we're just going to stick this one on and take it out, and especially in the field, this is very useful,
because it takes less space, so you just carry those and then just put them in here.
Next thing that we're going to need, which they don't provide, is a receiver.
Now, I'm going to be using the XM Plus radio here.
If you're using FlySky, then they have other receivers.
However, I'll have some iBus receivers, which are FlySky receivers linked down below,
and I'll also have some FRSky receivers for the FRSky system.
So again, I'm using XM Plus.
They're super cheap.
They get great distance and really great to use overall.
All right, so now let's take a closer look at what the package actually gives you.
It gives you a bunch of propellers, which is something you're going to need,
and that's quite a lot, which is really nice, and they've also labeled them for you.
So this would be the R.
This would be the normal, and we'll get into how to place these in a bit.
Now, they provide you with the four motors, almost cut to the exact length you'll need,
but I'm going to show you a nice trick to keep it super clean
and reduces your chance of actually ruining something when soldering these motors.
So they give you the motors.
They're 1105, 8,500 kV.
Sorry, 1104, 8,500 kV.
And the 8,500 kV is what I consider the sweet spot for these types of builds
because you can run either a 2SHV or a 3SHV and still enjoy and get a bunch of efficiency.
I will also have these motors tested on my benchmark in a later video
so we can compare it to the other motors in the market.
Now, they will give you every single connector you're going to need,
and what's really nice about this, you're not going to have to solder much.
All you're going to have to solder is your receiver, the XT30, and the motors, and that's about it.
So here we have three wires, five, so with the two here, so that's five wires.
And then here we have three times three, which is, oh, sorry, three times four, which is 12.
So we have a total of 17 things to solder, and everything else is using connectors.
So also something really nice with the kit is they give you the camera already pre-soldered and ready
with just the connectors here, and I'll show you where those go.
Those will go on the flight controller.
All we have to do is connect them, insert it into the 3D printed part to hold it in place,
and we'll be done with the camera in VTX, which makes our life really, really easy.
Also, the ESC they're using is actually a pretty good ESC.
I'm quite surprised at the ESC they're using.
I'm pretty sure you'll probably break the thing before you ever burn this ESC.
But then again, this is all theoretical.
Just because the filtration is really good, especially for something of this size,
and the fact that they even provide you with an installed 150 microfarad low ESR capacitor here.
And it is a Rubicon, which is pretty insane.
That's a well-known brand.
It's a pretty good brand here.
However, we're going to have to shorten these leads,
or you're more than likely to actually ruin this thing if these two touch the carbon fiber frame
because it's going to be sitting solo to the frame.
So once we get into that step, we'll take a closer look at that.
Now, for the flight controller, they're providing us with an F4 flight controller,
which is really great.
And it has all the features.
We have the OSD here.
We have, I think, an MPU 6000 gyro, USB.
Obviously, everything has USB.
And connectors for everything you're going to need.
So usually, I'd recommend we start with the flight controller here.
But the flight controller doesn't need anything soldered onto it.
And it's just connectors.
So we're going to keep it for later.
So for this ESC, it does matter which way you place it,
or else you have a nightmare and you won't know why.
With the arrow here pointing forward, this should be on top.
Because if it's not on top, it'll never fly.
Because the motor ordering will be completely different.
So keep that in mind.
Now, when I mentioned earlier that the motor wires were almost perfect length.
So instead of cutting them and making ourselves a bit more time,
and just making it more time consuming,
we can do a nice little trick that'll make it look like a professional's job.
All right.
So the first thing now I want to do is I want to just apply power.
I have this little cheap wool adapter that actually fits here,
and it's 12 volts.
And we can go ahead and start this guy up.
I just want to see what temperature I have it set to,
because I don't know.
400, which is maximum.
This comes with different crazy firmwares that you can set up.
I just left it on default.
And we can watch how quickly it heats up.
It depends on the power supply that you're using for it.
It just dictates how fast it heats up.
So we'll just let that heat up real quick.
Now, something you should always be aware of here.
If you're going to set your temperature slightly higher than,
let's say, 350 degrees Celsius,
you want to add solder.
Keep adding solder onto this every, you know,
like a couple minutes or so,
and cleaning it off.
Because before you start soldering,
you always want it to look like this.
You want it to look super shiny and super clean.
And that means that the heat's going to transfer very quickly.
And you're not going to hold it there for half an hour.
Nothing happens.
And that is a usual case why, for example,
the wire would not stick to the pad.
And another thing to take note of here
is you don't want to hit it with the tip just like this.
You want to actually kind of get as much of a flat area as possible
to land on it.
So if it's not really melting,
then kind of just do this little twisting motion
and it'll push that wire right into place.
Now, I did hire a new assistant
and I've actually noticed a couple things he was doing wrong,
which I was really hoping that I'm going to come here
and show you today.
And I'm very happy that that's going to happen.
So for the ESC, what we want to do first,
we want to add the solder to the pads.
This is the top here.
But the trick here is we're going to add them to the bottom.
And why is that?
It's so we can make the motor wires really nice and clean.
So we're going to start adding solder to the pads.
Now, take a note of where I'm starting.
I'm starting from the left here,
but this is really dangerous
because I can have some solder come to here
and burn a component off.
So instead, I'm just going to go here
because I have less risk of actually burning anything
coming down to the right.
What I like to do first always is touch the pad
and then add the solder to both the pad
and the soldering tip.
And there we go.
We have our first little solder blob thingy.
Now, again, I'm touching half of the pad here
and I'm going to come and just add the solder on the pad.
And there we go.
Now, as you can tell,
my soldering iron tip is getting pretty full and dirty.
So I'm just going to clean it slightly.
Now, if you are using water,
the temperature will drop slightly.
So you'd want to just wait a tiny bit
and make sure the tip is back up to temperature here.
But we're soldering at 400 degrees right now.
So it should be pretty good.
And you can kind of see the technique.
Try to understand what I'm doing here.
And don't be scared of keeping the tip on for too long.
I mean, don't keep it on for like 30 seconds.
But it's fine if you keep it there for five seconds.
That's totally fine.
I'll even show you that right now.
So I have the tip.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine.
Nothing happened.
You see that?
And did you see how it flicked?
That's very dangerous
because this little solder blob right there
could have landed somewhere here
and I couldn't see it.
And once I applied the battery,
then the whole ESC could short circuit.
And then people start complaining,
oh, this is the worst product on the planet.
And that usually does happen actually quite a lot.
So we'll just add a little bit more here
and add a little bit more here.
You want to see them really shiny.
So that's really good.
There we go.
See, this last one wasn't really great.
So how would you fix one that's sticking up like this?
You kind of see that.
You just come in just really flat
and then just push out.
And that looks really great.
So now we've added that.
Now, what's really great with these wires
is they have some solder on them.
So it's just going to make our life a little bit easier.
Now, if they didn't, you'd want to strip them,
twist them and add solder
before you solder to the pads here.
So and again, keep in mind,
this is the bottom side right now.
And we're going to do something
a little bit different here.
So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to straighten out the wires
just like that.
And I'm actually going to install them like this.
So I'm going to do again,
start from this side
so I don't risk damaging a component here.
So I'm going to come like this
and then install that right there.
Now, a really nice technique to do this
is to heat up the pad first,
just slightly,
and then come in with the wire.
And you don't have to be in a hurry.
Just take your time
and put that into place.
Now, we didn't have much solder
on the pad already,
but we'll come back and fix that later.
Let's move on to the second one here.
So there we go.
So here's the other one.
We're going to add some heat,
melt the pad,
and then come back on top of the wire here.
There we go.
And we're going to do the same thing to this one.
You could trim these off.
I'd highly recommend you trim them off
before you start soldering.
So there we go.
And be careful touching the ESE.
It's actually toasty right now.
Really, really toasty.
So the whole idea of why I did it this way
is because when we flip it over,
it's going to look really nice once you install it.
So these motor wires will just go in like this
and they'll be really flat
and it'll just be perfect.
It's not going to have any bends or creases or anything
that's sticking out of the quadcopter
for it to catch on anything.
But as you can tell,
these were slightly longer than we'd like them to be.
And I'll come back and fix this later.
And here we're going to do one more together.
Now, if you're going to cut wire,
never cut wires on top of any component
because it could also create a pretty big nightmare.
So I'm going to trim these slightly a bit here
and I'm going to do the same thing.
And again, taking I am on the bottom again,
there is no arrow here.
Now, the motor wire order doesn't really matter right now.
So because the whole idea here is
you can always anytime
if the motor is not spinning in the correct direction,
just flip any two wires
and it'll spin in the right direction.
So don't stress that part too much right now.
There we go.
And right now I'm not really heating up the pad
because it's a really small pad
and the heat is going to transfer really well.
So here, I just want to...
There we go.
All right.
So this is on 400 right now.
So you're going to have the same exact experience as me
while you're soldering.
Just make sure you're comfortable.
That's one of the most important things
when you're soldering, in my opinion,
is you're comfortable.
Okay.
Nothing is touching.
They're very well-placed paths.
They're very far apart from each other.
And this one, again,
I'm going to come back and fix up later on.
All right.
So I'm going to skip the rest of the motors
and then we'll see what is the next step.
All right.
So now when we're done,
we should have something that looks like this.
Now, the next thing I want to do
is actually remove this low ESR capacitor.
And it's going to be a little bit tricky
because we're going to have to heat up this side
because it's actually sticking in
through the hole right here.
Or we can do something just a lot easier
and we can actually just cut it.
I mean, that'll just work really great.
There we go.
We don't really have to worry about these
and they can even stay in there.
It's not really a big problem.
All right.
So now once the capacitor is removed or cut off,
we're left with shorter leads
and this is exactly what we want.
However, what we also want to do is
since it was on the bottom side,
we actually want to put it on the upper side.
However, we're going to leave this step for now
and bring in our XT30
where our battery will be connected,
supplying power to the whole micro quadcopter here.
Now I want to install this on the bottom side
and you'll see why
once we actually start putting this together,
it reduces the chances of the positive and negative
touching the carbon fiber frame
because it is conductive
so we don't have a short circuit
and blow the whole thing up.
So I'm going to come in
and I'm just going to add solder to the pad.
Same thing we did with the motor wires.
Same thing here.
Now, if you have the same soldering iron,
you need to take something into consideration.
If you leave it for a while,
then it'll just go into sleep mode
and drop the temperature.
So you might just have to wait
just a tiny bit for it to come back.
It won't drop it all the way to zero
and it'll quickly gain its temperature back.
So now we've added solder to that.
Now, here's a really nice technique.
I usually like to bring my solder
and just stand it up straight,
even though these have solder on it,
but I don't know how old it is.
So I stand it up straight
and then I would come in,
add solder to the bottom of my soldering iron,
tip,
and then start following along
just like this while holding the wire.
And now I have a really nice solder on the wire.
However, you need to take something into consideration.
The wire will get really hot
and it's actually really toasty right now.
So as you can tell,
I'm not holding it anymore.
So keep that in mind also.
Heat is real,
especially when you're soldering.
It might not look like there's no heat,
but there's a ton of heat.
And if it touches you,
you're going to burn yourself.
All right.
So now we're going to install the battery
into place here or the XT60.
And again,
look,
we are on the bottom side of the board.
So I'm going to heat up the pad
because these are bigger pads.
And then I'm going to come in
with the soldering iron on top of the wire.
And that should give us a really nice connection.
And that wire got really hot very fast.
So here we go.
And again,
make sure the plus is the red wire
and the minus or the negative is the black wire.
And there we go.
Try to resist the heat
and keep it into place
after you move the soldering iron
for everything to cool.
So now we're basically almost done.
All we need to solder here now
is the low ESR capacitor back into place.
And how does this go back into place?
Well,
wherever these dash signs are,
this will go to the ground,
which is the negative.
And then the other side
is just going to go to the positive.
And here,
since we know we put these in the correct way,
so we just put the negative side to the black here
and then the other side to the red.
So let's do this together here.
Now,
it's also really nice to add solder onto this.
It'll help slightly transfer the heat a little bit better.
And again,
I'm just going to stand up my solder
and just touch it here.
Just add on this.
Sometimes it won't stick.
It might not look like anything,
but it'll help in the long run here.
All right.
And this side where it has the dashes,
as you can tell,
is going to go to the ground.
But I'm going to start with the positive
because I think it'll be a little bit easier for me.
So I'm going to push this one
a little bit out of the way for now.
We could always bring it back into place.
So I'm going to heat up the pad.
Now we're on top of the ESC here.
So I'm going to heat up the pad here.
And then I'm going to bring in this guy into place.
You don't want to heat up the pad too much
because it might desolder the bottom one.
So keep that in mind.
All right.
Now I'm going to do the same thing here.
I'm going to heat up the pad.
Try not to touch anything like I did.
Okay.
There we go.
And that should not be touching anytime soon
because now the frame,
the carbon fiber is on the bottom here.
Even if this were to bend,
it's not going to touch the frame
because this is acting as an insulator
because it's pushing it away.
However, if this twists and these two touch together,
then you'll have a really big problem.
This will probably pop,
but it's not really high voltage,
but you know, just, yeah, just be careful.
So now the ESC is basically done
and it looks like a moving spider here.
Look at this.
Wait.
All right.
So now we have the frame into place
and you want to bring in the longest screws
and there's only four of these guys.
So let's bring those into place.
We're just going to install them
and keeping them standing.
Up for now.
This is the easiest way to do it.
So right now they're just standing into place.
I'm going to lift this up.
They're going to go right in,
flip it over and then put it down.
So now the screws are all standing up here.
We're going to get any four of these,
you know, these little dampeners here.
I'm just going to install them into the frame.
So now we have one on each screw here.
So the thing is,
I don't want to lift it up
because they're all going to come down
unless I hold it like this.
There you go.
You can kind of see that now.
So the next step is obviously insert the ESC,
but it does matter how you insert the ESC.
You want the holes to be on the side
so the battery will hold like this
unless you want the battery in another way.
That's your decision.
But usually the battery is forward and back.
So you want these to be on the sides,
the holes to be on the side.
And then we're going to figure out where's the front.
We're going to call that the front.
So we want to make sure that the arrow is on top
so we can see it
and that it's pointing forward.
And that is perfect.
And we're just going to slide this guy right in.
And now we're going to install the motor screws,
which I'll skip over.
However, the screw is going to be this one
and it's not going to be very hard to find it
because you only get four long screws
and a bunch of these little ones
that are exactly the same size.
And those are for your motors.
So I'm going to go ahead and start doing that.
All right.
So once the motors are installed,
it's going to look something like this.
Now what you want to take note of is
it's going to kind of act like a spring
because of the motor wire.
So what you want to do is push kind of hard,
just allow them to bend into place here.
Make sure all the motor wires are going from the inside part
to make your life a little bit easier.
So the next step is to add more of these little rubber ones
and they're all the same size.
They're actually, it seemed like it used to be like a tube
and they just had one guy cutting it piece by piece.
So they're not all cut perfect,
but I mean, what do you expect for 70 bucks or something?
So here's the arrow pointing forward.
Now this is very important also.
So the arrow is pointing forward.
You want to find the arrow also on the flight controller,
which is right there.
It's right in the middle right there.
It's saying this way.
So I'm going to install the quadcopter like this
and that's the arrow.
And then I have my four rubbers here.
So there we go.
My arrows forward.
Awesome.
So now we have those set into place.
Now I'm going to bring in some more rubbers
right on top of this.
They provide you with a total of 12, 12, no, nine, no 12.
So they give you a total of 12 here
and we have those set into place.
And I'm just going to give you an example here
without having to lose these.
So you can kind of see how it is.
We have one rubber, two rubber, three rubber here.
All right.
So now let's connect the electronic speed controller
or the ESC to the flight controller.
And it's done with this connector right here.
It's the biggest and shortest one.
So this connector is going to connect right into the big connector
up in front of the flight controller, which is the arrow.
That's going to go straight down.
Now, if it's not going in, then you want to flip the connector
and just be careful.
Don't force it in.
It'll go in very nicely if it's in the correct orientation.
There we go.
That's really nice.
We're going to bend this slightly here
because we don't want this hanging out later on
and getting caught with a propeller.
So now the ESC is actually connected.
So if we actually gave this power right now, the motors would light up
and the flight controller will light up and just about everything.
All we're missing are the camera and the receiver.
So let's go ahead and prepare the receiver
and I'll show you how this will actually work.
So I'm going to just cut these off just like that.
And these are not silicone for some reason or some sort of...
So stripping these might be a bit difficult
if you don't have the correct tools
or you don't have the experience to do it.
So I just did it with a little cutter right here.
All right.
So now I've gone ahead and twisted the wires up top here.
Once I stripped them, I'm just going to add some solder to these
because these are going to go into our receiver here.
And the other side where the white connector is,
is going to go into the flight controller.
So I'm going to trim these wires because they're a bit too long.
And again, don't cut or solder on top of any electrical component
nor the motors themselves.
So keep that in mind.
So here I have my XM plus radio
and I'm going to go ahead and solder onto it.
Now, if I remember correctly, this is SBUS.
And then I think it's 5 volt, then it's ground.
But I could be wrong.
I'll double check later, but I'm going to install them like that right now.
So if you had IBUS, then the yellow wire would be your signal, your IBUS.
And if you had SBUS, then the yellow wire would be your SBUS.
However, we do need to make a modification on the flight controller for the receiver to actually work,
which is choosing if it's going to be IBUS or if it's going to be an SBUS.
And this is very important that you know the difference
and know what your transmitter could broadcast that.
All right.
So now we have the receiver here.
So the modification we're going to have to do to the flight controller
is going to be somewhere pretty, pretty tiny, which is these three pads right here.
Now, if you're going to be using SBUS, these three pads here,
the middle one is going to have to be bridged with the left one.
If you're using IBUS or PPM, then the middle one is going to have to be bridged with the right one.
Don't bridge all of them together.
So let's try to attempt this together here.
This is really nice, but I wish these pads were slightly larger to help new people
because it can be pretty hard.
See, like right now, you see how difficult it is for me to solder?
That's because it went to sleep mode and then the temperature now is just coming back up.
All right.
So now they're bridging.
I do apologize.
I just looked up and it turns out I had it off camera
because I had to bring it closer to me.
And you can see now the middle one is bridged with the left one here
because I'm using SBUS.
And again, if you're IBUS, you bridge the middle one with the right one.
And that's what we did here.
So now our receiver is ready and we're basically done.
So we just got to connect everything up together.
All right, guys.
So next we want to install the camera into the little canopy here.
Now, I'd highly recommend you add some like double-sided tape behind the VTX.
Now, it's very important that you see the solder is coming up from this side.
And also you have this little extra piece taken out.
It's telling you, oh, the antenna is going to go on this side.
So it has the hole for the button here.
Now, this will go into sideways.
If you have it the other way, it'll just it just won't fit.
So you have to put it in the correct way.
And the wires, I've routed them through the back of the VTX down this hole.
So now to know where these actually connect.
Well, let's take a closer look.
So here's the arrow.
The VTX is going to go here or the four pin connector is going to go here
because it's a four and a three pin connector.
So this is the VTX here and that's in.
And then the other one is the front one here.
So again, here's the arrow.
The USB is on the left.
So this one here is where the camera would go in.
And if you actually take a closer look at your board, if you do have this,
you'll see the word cam right in between the big connector and the little connector.
So now we have that in place.
And obviously, we want the camera to point forward.
So now once you put the nuts in place, don't think you have to tighten it from up here.
So what we're going to do is we're going to have something holding up from the top
and then we'll just use the screw driver from the bottom or the hex driver from the bottom
to actually tighten it as we please.
Now, try not to bend the VTX antenna so much because it'll probably end up breaking.
And that goes for a lot of wires.
So that goes even for motor wires as well.
So keep that in mind.
Try not to keep hitting it by mistake because soldering one of those back into place
is much more difficult, especially if you're new.
All right.
So right now we're just tightening everything here.
And like I mentioned before, you don't have to keep it.
Just get the nut to grip.
And then that's what she said.
Yeah.
So just get the nut to grip.
And that should be good in that perspective.
I had to redo this part a bunch of times because that's what she said.
All right.
And this is how it's supposed to look like when it's complete.
Really nice.
Really simple.
The guts are kind of sticking out, but that was the whole idea here.
It's supposed to be all exposed, super light, 20 by 20 stack, which is actually pretty good
that it's using a 20 by 20 stack.
And again, if you take a look at the low ESR capacitor, this is the reason why I told
you you want to solder it on top of the ESC instead of the bottom.
So the battery wires here will not allow it to bend any further and touch this carbon
fiber because it was also pretty long.
So it would easily touch the carbon fiber, short circuited the whole thing.
So keep that in mind.
That's something really important.
Also, if you're new, I actually don't recommend you add your motor wires to the bottom of the
ESC.
I'd probably do it on top of the ESC.
It'd probably be a little bit easier and keep the extra slack and do something else with
it.
But if you just push it, it'll be fine.
But it might be a bit fiddly for you if you don't have much experience.
Also, the VTX here, it seems pretty stable, but I would definitely add some sort of something
to hold it in place.
I wouldn't add a zip tie because zip ties usually will tend to rip off components from
here.
So I'd probably add some double sided tape right below here.
Hot glue won't work because if you add hot glue, it'll just basically melt because these
do get pretty toasty.
And for this antenna here, I'd want to secure it with possibly some sort of a zip tie that's
going to go through here to here and just stick out like that.
And then I'll just heat shrink something on top of it.
And I'll actually do that.
All right.
So what I've done here is I should have actually left the zip tie slightly longer.
But what I've done is obviously I brought a little fatter heat shrink, put it on top,
and now it's holding the VTX with the heat shrink.
And that's not going anywhere.
It's just going to stay there.
And you don't want this to keep playing because it'll eventually break off the solder like
with any other wire.
And it's looking pretty nice to be honest.
I really like that yellow on there.
Now what you'll be left with is the receiver.
Right now it's like one in the morning and I really am tired and I just not going to have
a nice solution for this just yet.
But you can get creative.
Like what I'm thinking of doing is probably putting it somewhere here on the side because
there are some holes.
Put a heat shrink around this and then use double-sided tape to hold it into place.
I wouldn't put this on top of the flight controller because this is loose.
And then these little touches will touch the gyro and make it do weird stuff.
So you'll just not have a really pleasant experience and you won't know why.
So the best thing overall to do is to put it somewhere here on the side just like this.
And I'll figure that out in a later video.
Or I might even design and 3D print something else for this quadcopter and I'll share it
with you guys.
So I'll be flying this within the next two days once the rain clears up because now we're
starting to rain here.
And I'll show you the final result of how I got it to be and share everything else with
you guys.
But this is how you build it.
All you need to do is find a placement for your receiver.
And it's 1 in the morning right now so I'm really tired and I can't really think of anything
to do for that.
And again, all the links are down below.
If you could check them out, it does really support the channel.
I'll have links to the batteries to use for this.
I'll also have the links for the heat shrinks, the tools I use, and that soldering iron that
we just used for this whole build here.
And I'll see you in the next one.
Peace out.