Today in the workshop we're working with operational amplifiers.
You'll see how op amps work and how to use them in several popular configurations.
We'll also build a light activated switch, a dual power supply,
and we'll use op amps with an Arduino.
We're back in operation today, so welcome to the workshop.
Well, hello and welcome to the workshop,
and today we're going to be working with operational amplifiers,
more commonly known as op amps.
Now, op amps have been available in integrated circuit format for about six decades now,
and during that time they have been used in thousands and thousands of different analog designs.
One of the reasons for their popularity is because they are so versatile.
You can literally configure an op amp in a couple of dozen different ways,
and each of those configurations can be considered to be an analog building block
that you can use to build more complex circuitry.
Op amps can also be used to interface analog electronics to digital electronics.
Op amps are also extraordinarily inexpensive.
In fact, one of the op amps we're using today is a quad op amp that costs all of 40 cents,
so each op amp costs a dime.
Now, what we are going to do today is we're going to, of course,
start off by learning a bit about op amps,
and then we're going to put some of that theory into practice.
We're going to take an op amp, put it on a sonless breadboard,
and wire it in a number of different configurations.
After that, I'm going to show you how we can use an op amp with a microcontroller.
We're going to connect one to an Arduino Uno.
After that, we're going to build a little project,
a light-sensitive switch that is built with an op amp
and will probably cost you about $2 in components to put together.
And finally, many op amps need a dual power supply,
a supply with both a positive and a negative component,
while most of us have benched supplies that only are single power supplies.
So we're going to build a converter that converts a single supply to a dual supply,
and, of course, that converter is going to be built with an op amp.
I told you these things are versatile.
So let's start off by learning a bit more about operational amplifiers.
An op amp is a high-gain differential amplifier.
It has both a positive or non-inverting and negative or inverting input.
An op amp amplifies the differences between these two input voltages.
These devices are characterized by having a very high input impedance
and a very low output impedance.
Originally, operational amplifiers were developed for analog computers.
Analog computers used voltages to represent numbers.
The first operational amplifier was built with vacuum tubes in 1941.
The UA702 was the first integrated circuit operational amplifier,
and it was designed in 1963.
The schematic symbol for an operational amplifier
is chosen as a triangle with a number of connections to it.
On the top, we have the positive power,
and on the bottom, the negative power.
Most operational amplifiers require a bipolar power supply
with both positive and negative components.
There are two inputs in the op amp,
an inverting input and the non-inverting input.
Note that the inverting input on top
and the non-inverting on the bottom is not a convention,
and when you see op amps drawn in schematic diagrams,
you can see it drawn the other way around as well.
It just depends what looks better on the diagram.
Finally, the output of the op amp is at the point of the triangle.
In order to visualize how an operational amplifier works,
first we need to power it up.
We will use a bipolar power supply for the op amp
that has both a positive and a negative component.
Note that the power supply has a common ground point.
This ground point is a reference point.
We'll also connect two input voltages to our operational amplifier,
V1, which is connected to the inverting input,
and V2, which is connected to the non-inverting input.
Again, the two voltages reference the same common ground point.
If we apply a voltage of 4 volts to V1 and 6 volts to V2,
that'll create a difference of positive 2 volts.
Since this is a positive difference,
our output will be positive,
and the greater difference, the greater the output will be.
If we increase V1 to 9 volts,
then our difference will be negative 3 volts,
and so our output will go negative.
Again, the amplitude of the output will depend
on the amount of difference between the two inputs.
If we reduce V1 to 6 volts and keep V2 at 6 volts,
there'll be no difference between the two inputs.
Therefore, the output of the operational amplifier will be zero.
By itself, an operational amplifier has a great deal of gain.
In fact, the typical op amp has a gain of 100,000 times or more.
Since this is likely too much for our circuit,
we need to regulate it,
and we can do that by applying feedback,
which is to take the output of the op amp
and apply it to one of its inputs.
Over here, I show it being applied to the inverting input.
This will actually create an amplifier whose gain is only one.
In other words, what goes into the amplifier will be what comes out.
Since we might want a little bit more gain than that,
but not the infinite amount of gain that we get with the open loop,
we can apply a feedback resistor.
The value of the resistor will determine the gain of the amplifier,
and the higher the value of the resistor,
the higher the amplifier's gain will be.
A common configuration for an operational amplifier
is as an inverting amplifier.
An amplifier whose output is 180 degrees out of phase with its input.
The two components used with the operational amplifier in this configuration
are the input resistor and the feedback resistor,
and these two components determine the gain of the inverting amplifier.
Another common configuration is the non-inverting amplifier,
an amplifier whose output is in phase with its input.
Once again, the feedback and divider resistor will determine the gain of this type of amplifier.
A unity gain buffer is an amplifier that has a gain of 1.
This is also known as a voltage follower,
and takes advantage of the fact that the operational amplifier
has a very high input impedance and very low output impedance.
Unity gain buffers are often used throughout op-amp circuitry.
The voltage summing amplifier is an application from the op-amp's analog computer days.
The op-amp will output a sum of the three different input voltages.
The feedback can be used to amplify this
and effectively do a multiplication on the voltage.
Another mathematical operation that could be done with an op-amp
is as a differential amplifier.
In this case, the output of the amplifier will be the difference between V in 1 and V in 2.
Integration is another mathematical operation that operational amplifiers can perform,
and when performed upon a square wave, it can turn it into a triangle wave.
You can also input a triangle wave into an integrator
and come out with an approximation of a sine wave.
And the differentiating amplifier performs a differential operation on the voltage coming in.
You'll notice its effect on a square wave here.
An open-end comparator is a very common configuration for an operational amplifier.
A comparator has a reference voltage and an input voltage,
and if the input voltage exceeds the reference voltage,
the output voltage will go high, or to positive Vcc.
If it's below the reference voltage, it'll go low, or down to the ground level.
Comparators are often used to interface analog electronics to digital electronics.
A low-pass active filter is a very common application in audio.
A low-pass filter allows low frequencies to pass while attenuating high frequencies,
and it can be built as follows with an op-amp.
A different configuration creates a high-pass active filter,
a filter that allows higher frequencies to pass, but attenuates lower ones.
And a multivibrator is a configuration which an operational amplifier can produce a waveform.
In this diagram, we are producing a square wave whose frequency is determined by the value of Cx and Rx.
R2 and R1 can be used to determine the duty cycle and the amplitude of our square wave.
Now, in selecting an operational amplifier, you should go and take a look at the spec sheets,
as they'll give you all the information you need to know.
There's quite a bit of info here, and some of it may be confusing,
so here are some of the key specifications to look out for.
The open-loop gain of the operational amplifier defines the gain of the op-amp without any feedback.
Now, an ideal op-amp would have an infinite open-loop gain.
In the real world, values typically range from 20,000 to 200,000 or even more.
Now, keep in mind that the maximum output that your operational amplifier can give
is going to be limited by the power supply voltage and not the gain.
The input impedance of the op-amp is defined as the ratio of the input voltage to the input current.
Impedance is a factor that is measured in ohms.
An ideal op-amp would have an infinite input impedance,
and real-world values for op-amp input impedance are typically several megohms,
meaning op-amps won't load down the driving circuitry.
The output impedance of an op-amp is also an important specification.
An ideal op-amp would have a zero output impedance.
In the real world, the values are typically about 100 to 20,000 ohms.
The gain bandwidth product, or GBP, is a very important specification
as it refers to the frequency response of your op-amp.
Now, an ideal op-amp would, of course, have an infinite bandwidth.
The bandwidth of the op-amp is limited by the gain bandwidth product,
and this is defined as the bandwidth with an open-loop gain of 1.
In the real world, op-amps typically have values from 500 kHz to 20 MHz or more.
The offset voltage is the output voltage when the difference between the inputs is zero.
An ideal op-amp would have no offset voltage.
In the real world, the values typically are 1 mV to 10 mV,
and this is an inaccuracy in the op-amp.
Some operational amplifiers have an offset pin to allow adjustment of the offset voltage.
Op-amps are available in several different packages, including dip and surface mount.
You can get single, dual, or quad op-amps in the same package.
Op-amps are available using both single and traditional dual power supplies.
You also might see the term rail-to-rail designs.
These are op-amps whose output can go all the way to their VCC.
On most op-amps, the output is slightly less than VCC,
unless it is specified as being rail-to-rail.
So now let's take a look at a couple of op-amps and put them to use.
Now here are a number of op-amps that I got out of my parts drawer,
and each one of these is unique in its own right.
Some of them are single op-amps, some are dual, some are quad.
There are op-amps here that are single supply, and there are dual supply op-amps as well.
Now all of these are in dip or dual inline packages.
Of course you can get op-amps in other packages,
but for experimenting, the dip package is what we will use,
because they fit into a soddeless breadboard.
Now I'm sure you've probably worked with them before,
but if you haven't, on a dip package there is usually a notch over at the front,
and quite often a dot like you'll see over here,
and that indicates pin 1.
So when you're orienting things, that's the way it is.
And they'll be numbered 1, 2, 3, 4 down this side,
and then they'll go 5, 6, 7, 8 up on the other side.
And of course for a 14 or a 16-pin package, the number follows accordingly.
And so let's take a look at the characteristics of some of these operational amplifiers.
The LM324 is a very popular quad operational amplifier.
This device uses a single supply and can handle 32 volts maximum VCC.
The LM324 is used in a lot of equipment, especially because of its low, low price.
Currently this retails on DigiKey for 40 cents per unit,
and so when you consider you get 4 op amps in it,
they work out to about a dime per op amp.
The NE5532 is another very popular operational amplifier.
This is a dual op amp, and it uses a dual power supply.
Each power supply can have a maximum of 15 volts.
This is a high performance operational amplifier with very low noise and distortion,
so it can be used in audio equipment designs.
Another popular operational amplifier is the LM358.
It's also a dual op amp, and has essentially the same pinout as the NE5532.
However, the LM358 has been wired to use a single power supply.
This is a very common operational amplifier,
and as its power supply can range from 3 to 32 volts DC,
it can also be used to interface analog and digital circuitry.
The TL072 is a dual operational amplifier that uses dual power supplies.
This is a very popular audio amplifier for audio designs,
as it has a very high GBP, and a very high slew rate,
and very, very low noise and distortion.
The CA3140 is a single operational amplifier that uses a dual power supply,
and has a maximum GBP of 4.5 MHz.
The CA3240 is the same operational amplifier in a dual op amp pack.
These op amps are often used in automotive and industrial designs,
as they incorporate both MOS and bipolar transistors
for a very high input impedance,
and a very high current output capability.
The MCP6002 is a dual operational amplifier
that uses a single power supply,
and that power supply has a maximum of only 6 volts.
It has a 1 MHz GBP.
The MCP6022 is the same operational amplifier with a much higher GBP.
Because of the voltages these operational amplifiers use,
they have been designed to be used with logic circuits,
as they're perfect for both 3.3 and 5 volt logic.
They also use rail-to-rail input-to-output,
so they can swing all the way up to their power supply voltage.
They're very low noise and distortion,
and they consume very little current.
Okay, enough of the op amp theory.
Let's put some of it into practice.
We're going to take an op amp and put it onto a SOTELIS breadboard,
and wire it in a number of different configurations,
so we can see how these building blocks are really created.
Now, the op amp we're going to be using is the NE5532,
which is a very common operational amplifier.
It requires a dual power supply, but don't worry about it.
You can just use a couple of 9 volt batteries for these experiments.
So let's see how the NE5532 is wired up,
and then we'll proceed to use it in a number of basic configurations.
I'll be basing all of my experiments around an NE5532 operational amplifier.
This is a very inexpensive and easy to obtain device.
This is a dual op amp,
and it contains two operational amplifiers that are wired as follows.
Pin 3 of the device is connected to the non-inverting input on amplifier 1.
Pin 2 is connected to the inverting input on that amplifier,
and pin 1 is connected to the output of op amp 1.
Pin 5 is connected to the non-inverting input of amplifier 2.
Pin 6 is its inverting input,
and pin 7 is the output of op amp 2.
The positive end of the power supply is connected to pin 8,
and the negative end to pin 4.
Note that there is no connection on the op amp for ground.
The positive and negative power supply for NE5532 can be up to 15 volts,
and a very convenient way of powering these for our experiments is just to use two 9-volt batteries.
Connect the positive side of one of the 9-volt batteries to pin 8, which is the positive VCC,
and connect the negative side to pin 4, which is the negative VCC.
The remaining two battery terminals are tied together, and this is our ground point.
Again, there is no ground connection to the NE5532.
We will be using this basic circuit with all of the different configurations that I am about to show you.
Now the first configuration that we will examine with the NE5532 is obviously the simplest configuration there is,
and that is the unity gain buffer.
You will notice that in this configuration the output of the op amp is fed back into its inverting input,
and that the input to the op amp is fed into the non-inverting input.
Wired like this, the op amp will have a gain of 1,
so what goes in is exactly what will go out.
And you might think that this is a pretty useless circuit, but it actually is not.
The unity gain buffer is also called a voltage follower,
and it can be used to take advantage of the fact that the op amp has a very high input impedance,
and a low output impedance.
If you want to mix several signals together,
you can proceed each one of these with a unity gain buffer,
as though not to overload an input.
The unity gain buffer is a circuit that you will see used quite often in op amp designs.
And so here we have our first experiment, the voltage follower,
and of course the very simple circuit that it is.
You can take a look at how I've got it on the breadboard.
I've got my two batteries each going to the different rails,
and I've also got a jumper over here,
and that connects the negative of the positive supply to the positive of the negative supply,
if that makes sense to you.
And that is the common ground.
So just make certain that you realize that on the bottom over here,
the red is actually a ground, and the blue is the negative voltage.
Otherwise, it's a very simple circuit, just wired up with a few jumpers.
When you're working with analog electronics on a soddeless breadboard,
you will find out that the breadboard does pick up a little bit of noise, etc.
Now these breadboards I have on the bottom of them,
they have a little aluminum plate that's supposed to help shield them,
but since it isn't grounded, I don't know if it's working or if it's even adding to the problem.
But you try to keep all your leads as short as you can.
If you're using resistors and capacitors,
try to use those to make the connections without any additional jumpers,
just so you get a more stable circuit.
So if you take a look on the oscilloscope,
you'll see what we've got are two sine waves.
The yellow one on the top is the input,
and the blue one on the bottom is the output.
And of course, they're exactly the same,
and that's what you would expect with a voltage buffer.
It just has a gain of one, so what goes in is what comes out.
And of course, the high impedance input can be used to buffer sections within your design.
Probably the most common configuration that you'll see an op amp used in
is as an inverting amplifier.
You'll see this used throughout audio equipment designs, for example.
Now this is how we're going to wire our NE5532 up as an inverting amplifier,
and we'll need two additional components.
An input resistor that's labeled as Rn,
and a feedback resistor that's labeled as Rf.
And both of these resistors in our case are going to be 1k.
Now you can see from the formula here that the gain of the amplifier
depends upon the ratio of these two resistors.
So with each of them being the same value,
our amplifier will have a gain of one.
If you want to change the gain of the amplifier,
you can do so by altering the values of the resistors.
And it is common to leave the value of Rn in place
and change the value of the feedback resistor, Rf.
If you wish, you could use a potentiometer for Rf instead of a fixed resistor,
so you could have a variable gain amplifier.
So let's wire this up and test it out.
Now here's the demo of our inverting amplifier.
I'm applying a 1kHz sine wave,
and that is the yellow one that you see over here on my A channel.
And the output channel is this one over here.
And as we can see, the output has been inverted 180 degrees,
thus an inverting amplifier.
But otherwise, it looks very good.
It's a very nice sine wave.
And again, this is one of the most popular configurations of an amplifier
that you can have using an op-amp.
Now the opposite of the inverting amplifier would of course be the non-inverting amplifier,
an amplifier whose output is in phase with its input.
And this is how we would wire up our NE5532 as a non-inverting amplifier.
Note that we're using the same two components,
the same resistors as we did with the inverting amplifier,
and that once again, the gain is dependent upon the ratio of the values of these resistors.
As with the previous design, you could change the feedback resistor if you wish
to change the gain of the amplifier,
or you could use a potentiometer to build a variable gain amplifier.
I should point out that the formulas I'm giving you for gain are actually approximations
because true formulas for amplifier gain
need to include the impedance of both the input and output devices.
But for most cases, these formulas should work fine
for you to calculate the gain of your op-amps.
So let's wire up our non-inverting amplifier and test it out.
And so now we have our non-inverting amplifier demonstration,
and as you can see, it's pretty well the same as the inverting amplifier,
with one obvious difference.
The output signal here is in phase with the input signal,
so it has not been inverted.
And between inverting and non-inverting amplifiers,
you can pretty well control the phase of the signal throughout your design,
and it's not uncommon to use a combination of both of these
in an audio design or in other op-amp circuitry.
Now the next circuit that we're going to look at
is also a very commonly used audio circuit,
and that's the low-pass active filter.
This is a filter that will allow low frequencies to pass
while attenuating the higher frequencies.
And this one is a very simple filter
that attenuates at a rate of 3 decibels per octave.
We can calculate the frequency that it operates as
by using the formula in the corner,
and you'll see that with the values that we have here,
it'll cut off at about 1592 hertz.
Now you can change the frequency, of course,
by changing the value of both the resistor and capacitor,
and in practice it's easier to change the capacitor to a fixed value,
and then trim the value of the resistor.
So let's wire this one up on the breadboard,
and check it out.
And so here's our low-pass filter demonstration
hooked up and visualized on the oscilloscope once again.
Now a low-pass filter, of course, will attenuate higher frequencies.
So right now we have a 1 kilohertz sine wave being fed into it.
The top waveform, the yellow one, is the input,
and the blue one at the bottom is the output.
So let's increase the frequency up a little bit.
And we'll go to 2 kilohertz,
and you'll notice the bottom has started to attenuate.
And as I go higher in frequency,
the top stays the same, but the bottom goes down.
And so now we're at 10 kilohertz over here,
and you can see it's quite a bit less than if I back off to 1 kilohertz.
And so our filter is working.
Now a simple filter like this only attenuates at about 3 decibels per octave,
but you can build more advanced filters that can attenuate at a higher rate or a sharper rate
using the same basic circuitry that we just used over here.
Now if we exchange the position of the capacitor and the resistor in our filter,
we can turn it into a high-pass active filter,
a filter that allows higher frequencies to pass while attenuating lower frequencies.
Once again, the formula for the filter is essentially the same,
and ours has a crossover of 1592 hertz.
Now high-pass and low-pass filters can be used to build things like tone controls,
equalizers, crossover networks, and to eliminate noise and circuits.
So they're very useful things to be able to know how to construct.
So let's wire this one up on our breadboard and check it out.
And here's the demonstration of the high-pass filter,
which of course has the opposite effect of the low-pass filter.
The higher the frequency is, the more of it it will permit through,
and low frequencies will be attenuated.
Now once again for the demo, the input waveform is the top one,
and the bottom one, the blue one, is the output.
And we're at 500 hertz right now.
We're going to go up in increments of 100 hertz this time so that you can see it.
And take a look at the level on the bottom as I increase the frequency.
So I'm going up in frequency now.
And as you can see, the level is increasing the higher I go in frequency.
And now I'm at 5 kilohertz, and the level is quite a bit higher.
I'll go back down so you can watch the effect in reverse.
And so a high-pass filter basically just lets high frequencies through
and attenuates the lower one.
And again, this is a very simple filter, 3 decibels per octave,
but you can cascade these to get a sharper filter.
Now in our final basic experiment,
we're going to use both of the op-amps in the NE5532.
And we're going to wire the first one as a multivibrator
that will produce a square wave.
The frequency of our square wave is going to be determined
by capacitors CF and resistor RF.
And so you could use a potentiometer for RF
if you want to make a variable frequency oscillator.
Resistors R2 and R1 will determine both the pulse width
and the amplitude of our square wave.
We're going to take the second op-amp in the NE5532
and wire it up as an integrator.
As you recall, an integrator performs a mathematical integration on a waveform.
We'll be using the value of 10k for R3,
100k for R1,
and C1 will be using 100 nanofarads.
Connect everything up
and connect it to the square wave oscillator that we created earlier.
We can then monitor both the square wave
and the output of the integrator,
which should be a triangle wave.
And here's a quick demonstration of our waveform generator.
And as you can see, the top waveform is the square wave
and the bottom one is the triangle wave.
The square is tilted a little bit at the top,
but the triangle wave is just about perfect.
And actually the tilting on the square
could probably be fixed just by adjusting the capacitance on my scope probe.
That may not be exactly accurate.
And so it works very well as a generator.
It's generating a frequency now of 1.88 kHz,
but of course you could alter that frequency
by changing the resistor and capacitor values.
So if you need to generate a waveform,
an operational amplifier is actually a great way to do it.
Now although they are analog circuits,
its operational amplifiers can also be used to glue together
analog and digital circuitry.
And there's a couple of methods they can use to do this.
One method that we've used before is to run an op amp as a comparator
and use the comparator with a digital input pin on a microcontroller.
Another thing you can do with an op amp is to use it as an amplifier
to amplify the signal for the analog to digital converter.
And that's what we're going to do right now.
We're going to take an op amp and use it to amplify a very small signal
and read it with the A to D converter on an Arduino Uno.
So let's go and see how we hook that up and then we'll put it to use.
Now here's the circuit that we're going to be using
to amplify the signal for our Arduino.
And we're building our amplifier around an MCP6002 op amp.
This op amp is an excellent choice
when you're working with digital circuitry as it is a single supply op amp
and it has a maximum supply voltage of only 6 volts.
It works perfectly with 3.3 and 5 volt logic.
So again, it's ideal for working with digital circuitry.
Now what we have here is essentially a classic amplifier design.
You can see the feedback loop in the light blue up there.
The capacitor across the resistor is just for stability
and to prevent it from going into oscillation.
The 100k pot you can use to control the gain of the amplifier.
And the output of the amplifier you'll also notice
is a 220 pF capacitor across it just for a little bit of noise reduction.
Now the input has a 100 nF capacitor.
You can see it on the yellow on the left side.
If you were going to be amplifying DC voltages,
you can eliminate the capacitor and just connect them directly.
But I've got this set up so that you could use audio voltages
from something like, let's say, a microphone for example.
Otherwise, it's a fairly basic circuit.
Note the 2.2 microfarad capacitor
that sits across the 5 volt and ground line.
You want to get that capacitor as close as you possibly can physically to the chip.
Ideally, you'll straddle the chip with that capacitor.
And the function of that capacitor
is to take some of the noise that might be on the line.
Remember, you're sharing 5 volts with an Arduino.
And microcontrollers and their peripherals
can sometimes put noise onto the line.
Now after you've got this all wired up in the breadboard,
you'll need to hook it up, of course, to the Arduino.
And the hookup is very simple.
The power supply for the circuit, the 5 volts,
will connect to the Arduino's 5 volts.
The ground will, of course, connect to the Arduino's ground.
And we're going to feed the output into analog input A0.
And so once you've got that wired up,
you can feed a signal into it and run a bit of code
and look at it with the Arduino.
So let's go and do that right now.
Okay, here's our demonstration of the Arduino
with the op-amp amplifier.
And you'll notice I've also added a signal generator
and an oscilloscope to the mix right now.
Now the signal generator is currently giving out
a 2 kilohertz sine wave at half a volt.
And it's being amplified by the amplifier.
What I've got the scope set to here right now
is one volt per division.
And so I've got just about a full output over here.
It's amplifying just about 10 times.
Now I'm going to reduce the level of the input over here.
And now we're at 0.1 of a volt.
And we've still got about a 1 volt sine wave over here.
I'm just going to play with the gain control a bit
just to see the effect that has.
And over here, I can get it so high,
I can clip it right now, if you can see that.
And I can also adjust it down.
So I've got a lot of gain over here,
a lot of potential gain.
This is a 0.1 volt signal that I'm getting in here.
And I'm amplifying it almost to the full voltage right now.
Now if we take a look at the Arduino side of things,
the sketch is very, very simple.
We start off by defining the pin that we're using,
analog pin A0,
and a variable just to hold the value of that.
In the setup, we'll set up the serial monitor.
That's all we do.
And then in the loop,
we're just going to do an analog read to that pin,
assign the value to that variable.
And then we're going to do a serial print lin
of that variable to the display.
And then we're going to delay for 50 milliseconds
and do the whole thing over and over again.
And actually, it looks better running on the plotter,
which is what I really wrote it for.
So let's put the plotter on.
And as you can see on the plotter,
you can see we do have a representation of our sine wave.
And the level is much, much higher
than you would expect from a 0.1 of a volt signal.
So this is a really great way of amplifying
and extending the analog to digital converter,
not just in an Arduino Uno,
but on any microcontroller,
because this op amp will work fine with 3.3 volts as well.
It's got a very good frequency response.
It's audio capable,
so you could use it with a very high quality
analog to digital converter.
And also there are two op amps in the package,
so you could actually build a second circuit
and amplify a second one of the A to D inputs
and really add a lot of versatility to your projects
with an op amp and a microcontroller.
Now, if I gave you the task of designing
a light sensitive switch,
one that would turn something on or off
based upon the absence or presence of light,
chances are you would probably start thinking
about using a microcontroller
with perhaps an LDR or a photo transistor on it.
And while that will certainly work,
there is a much easier way of doing this,
and that is, of course,
to use an operational amplifier.
We're going to build a small light sensitive switch
with an op amp that's just going to control an LED,
but you could extend it to use a relay
or a power transistor to control something else.
The best deal is that this entire design
is going to take about $2 worth of parts
and no programming required.
So let's go and take a look at the hookup for that.
Now here's the schematic for our light activated switch,
and we're building this around an LM358 op amp.
The LM358 is a very inexpensive
and commonly available device,
and it has an advantage in that it can work off
of a single power supply.
So we're going to power everything
with one 9-volt battery.
Now the output of the LM358
is going to a 220-ohm dropping resistor
and then to an LED.
So we're just going to be turning an LED on and off,
but of course you could change this for a relay
or a power transistor to drive something else.
Now essentially what we're doing here
is running this as a comparator
with a voltage divider consisting of the two 10k resistors
attached to the inverting input.
On the non-inverting input,
we have another voltage divider
which consists of the light dependent resistor
or photo cell and a 20k potentiometer.
You can adjust a 20k pot
to adjust the trip point over here.
So this is a very simple circuit.
Let's wire it up and give it a test.
And here's our light sensitive switch.
You can see the LED is on right now.
And if I go and cover the photo cell,
the LED goes off.
And so basically it's being triggered
whenever it sees light.
Now of course the LED is just an indicator.
You could replace the LED with a transistor
and a relay to drive something if you wanted to.
There's also another trick you can do with this.
So let me show that to you.
Right now I'm going to disconnect my LED
and connect it up another way.
I'm going to now put the anode
up to the positive power supply instead.
And now what we've got is the LED is off.
If I cover the photo cell,
the LED goes on.
So we've got the opposite arrangement right now.
It's detecting dark instead of light.
So you can wire it up either way that you want to,
which is pretty versatile.
And as I said, if you want to tie a transistor
or a relay onto the output,
you could drive something else.
So here we have a photoelectric controlled switch
that is not dependent upon a microcontroller
and a very simple and inexpensive thing to build.
If you need something like this,
this is a great way to go.
Now, as you've noticed,
many operational amplifiers require a dual power supply,
a power supply that has both a positive
and a negative component in reference to ground.
And you may not own a dual power supply.
My workbench supply, for example,
is just a single output power supply.
But there is a converter that you can build
to convert a single supply into a dual supply.
And the converter is based around an op amp.
So let's go and see how easy this is to wire up
and convert a single power supply
into a power supply we can use with operational amplifiers.
Now here's the circuit for our power supply converter.
And this is being built around an NE5532 op amp.
You could use another op amp if you wish,
providing it is an op amp made for dual power supplies.
I'm also using two output transistors,
a tip 31C and a tip 32C.
Now you could use different output transistors if you wish.
The key here is to use complementary transistors,
an NPN and a PNP transistor
that have otherwise the same characteristics.
The tip 31C and tip 32C
are capable of handling three amperes of current.
So we can power something with up to three amps here.
Although if you're going to go anywhere near the current rating,
you should probably put a heat sink on those transistors.
If you wish,
you could substitute a tip 41C and 42C
and go to six amperes.
You'll also need a couple of 100 microfarad filter capacitors
for the output.
And these need to be rated at at least the supply voltage.
So I would rate these at 35 volts or more.
Now the operational amplifier
has a voltage divider on the input
that is made of two 10k resistors.
And that's being applied to the non-inverting input.
And the inverting input is just taking feedback
from our reference or ground point on the output.
And it will adjust the operational amplifier
if the op amp finds itself going at a different reference point.
And this will keep the voltages regulated on the output side.
So it's actually a pretty simple circuit to hook up.
Make sure you've got it all hooked up correctly though
because you are dealing with your power supply voltages.
So let's put ours onto a breadboard
and check it out
and see if we can drive another op amp circuit
with our single to dual power supply converter.
And so here's a demonstration of my power supply splitter.
Now I've got it connected
to the square and triangle wave multivibrator
that we created a little bit earlier.
So I'm driving one of our circuits with this circuit.
I'm using my bench power supply
and it's giving out 20 volts right now.
And it's important to note that the bench power supply
has a floating output.
In other words, the negative side of the power supply
is not connected to ground.
And that's very important.
If this had been connected to ground,
I would have literally shorted everything out
when I connected my oscilloscope up over here.
And we certainly don't want that to happen.
But otherwise, this is the breadboard
with the splitter on it.
I think if you look very carefully down here,
you'll see the two power transistors.
And it is powering this circuit here.
And as you can see from the oscilloscope,
it is indeed working.
We've got the square wave and the triangle wave.
Now I've got a multimeter over here
and we'll measure a couple of voltage points.
Here is the positive voltage I've got right now.
The multimeter is tied to ground.
And I've got 9.98 volts.
So I'm not sure if you can see that.
And I'm going to go over to my negative side right now.
And I've got negative 9.96 volts.
So it's regulated pretty well.
Now, as I said earlier, when I showed you the design,
if you wanted to,
you could also put a couple of three-pin voltage regulators
on the output to regulate it even further.
But it actually splits the supply pretty well.
So this is a great solution
if you need a dual power supply for your op amps
and you don't have one.
Just use an op amp to take a single power supply
and make it into a dual one.
And so this concludes our look at operational amplifiers.
I do hope that you enjoyed the video.
And more importantly,
I hope it's opened up your eyes to the fact
that not everything has to be built
around the microcontroller.
You can build a lot of useful circuitry and projects
around analog components like operational amplifiers.
Now, if you want to get some more information about op amps
or if you want to get the circuits that I used today,
you will find all of that on the article
that accompanies this video
on the dronebotworkshop.com website.
And there's a link right below the video to that article.
When you're on the website, if you haven't yet,
please consider signing up for my newsletter.
It's not a sales letter.
It's something I send out now and then
to let you know about things that go on in the workshop
because sometimes things do go on in the workshop.
And the newsletter, of course, is absolutely free.
Another thing that's absolutely free
is the Dronebot Workshop Forum.
So if you're having a problem
with one of your op amp designs, get on the forum.
There are a lot of great people on the forum
who can help you out with your electronics projects.
And finally, if you haven't yet,
please subscribe to the YouTube channel.
I make videos about electronics, microcontrollers,
programming, and I think you would really enjoy them.
And all you need to do to subscribe
is to hit that little red subscribe button
that you'll find below the video.
And if you also hit the bell notification,
you will get notified every time that I make a new video,
assuming, of course, you enable notifications
in your web browser.
And with that said, please take care of yourself.
Please stay safe out there.
And I will see you soon here in the Dronebot Workshop.
Goodbye for now.
lessons.
Life is en Summit
Around theal mimics
principles
the
Music