Hello everybody out there in newbie land like I am just learning everything about droning
I guess you would call it got my wizard here and I've been recently wanting to move away from
switch arming on a single switch to I think stinger swarm is a one of the youtubers that I noticed
that was arming on multiple switches and so I just wanted to share with everyone how to actually set
that up so first of all in your transmitter you need to go in here and change your aux channels
so on this one I actually have the upgraded firmware so it can do up to 10 channels but you may only
have the six channels so your first four channels are these channels you know your throttle your yaw
and your pitch in your roll that's channel one through four so you really only have two other
channels to mess with on stock firmware and I only have a six channel receiver in here although I am
using it with iBus so I can use all 10 channels anyways I believe these are the defaults I tried
to set this back to default because I kind of already went through all this just to make sure it would
work and it does so I just want to show you guys how to do it basically I want to hit both of these
switches to arm so that was out of focus but basically to arm the quad I want to have to hit
both of these switches I want both down to arm I want if only this one is down I want it to beep
and if only this one is down nothing happens right so before I just had this to arm and I had this
for my modes you know I had angle and horizon and then acro you got to start by changing channel five
and six we're just going to pretend like those are the only two channels that exist here so I want
switch a and b to be on channel five so to do that you go into your aux channels and you just push
this until it says switch a plus b switch a plus b actually before I do that let me show you this let's
go into the display and you can see here this is channel five this is channel six channel seven okay
channel eight this is nine and ten okay so you can see all that on the display you can see how it works
there so this switch is full off full on so the throttle value or the the value is one thousand and two
thousand that's all you get right there so when we change it here in the aux channels what we're doing
is saying that we want to so when we change it here in the transmitter we go into channel five and we want
to set this to be switch a plus b okay and we want channel six to be on this switch so we're going to set that
one to switch C so there we go and we don't want switch C to also be on channel eight I mean I guess
it doesn't matter you don't have to get rid of these but I like to just kind of get rid of these so if
we keep going back I can put these all here like that so those things will be controlling the switches are
only going to affect channel five and six that doesn't actually affect anything if we don't set
it up in beta flight so now that we have that set up with aux five and a and b you can see here that
when we hit switch a we're only getting I don't know maybe 1350 on the value there or 1400 probably and
when we only hit this one we're only getting maybe 1600 or 17 maybe so both of them up and we have a
throw a value of a thousand on channel five both of them down we have a value of 2000 on channel five
and then this one is you know 1500 and 2000 because that's a three position switch so we're basically
getting four positions with these two switches now these two switches are affecting one channel and
giving us four different positions to choose from and we're really only going to need three one is going
to be beeper not armed and the other one is going to be not armed and not beeper and then last not beeper
and not and and armed so those are the only three states that we're really looking for so let's go ahead
over to beta flight and we'll see what that looks like in beta flight so here let me plug in I'm gonna
plug in the quad there we go and I'm actually gonna plug in the lipo as well so that we have the receiver
powered all right so here we are in beta flight and we're just gonna connect up and you can see if
we go over to the receiver tab here that you'll notice that if I flip switch one see the value we're
getting is 1333 there and then if I flip switch to 1667 there so and then if we flip both 2000 is the
power value so that's how we can have two switches affect one channel it's basically just four positions here we got
two times two so
one thousand thirteen thirty three sixteen sixty seven and two thousand those are the all four options
so to set this up in beta flight to do double switch arming all's we got to do is go into the modes tab
under arm you're going to add a range and this is channel one or ox one which is really channel five
that that might be confusing but that's how it works so ox one and we don't want it to arm unless we're way
up here and we don't want it to be down here in 1667 range which we're not I don't believe yeah that's
1500 there so we're just gonna slide up and why isn't it letting me make that smaller that's fine I guess
that's fine all right so save we are armed yeah we should probably unarm hello that was scary I did not
expect that all right so here we are unarmed and no beeper so how do we add the beeper
we want this range right here add range ox one there we go we want into this range but we don't really
care about anything else and it's down here we don't want it and of course when it's up here we don't want
it right so save uh yeah you probably shouldn't do this with props on I'm just terrible at my job here
so anyways that's that's all there is to that so yeah let's go ahead and set up the um modes or the uh
angle mode at least so we're going to put this on ox two and that's going to be right there at the
beginning and then horizon ox two in the middle there and then that will be angle mode so that's how
easy that is anyways thanks for watching and I hope this uh taught you something that you didn't already
know