Hey everybody, Kenneth Russell here. I hope you're doing great today. Today I'm talking about cables,
how to understand cables and their connectors. Check it out.
Well, if you're a musician or working in sound in any way, you're going to come across cables
and all different types of cables. And sometimes it can be kind of daunting if you're just getting
into it because there's all these different connectors. You don't know what they're called.
So let's talk about the connectors in the first half of this video. And then we're going to talk
about the cable itself in the second half of the video. By the way, a huge shout out to Hosea Cables
for sending me all these cables. And they're just awesome cables. I've been buying Hosea Cables for
years. If you're looking to buy an instrument cable for your guitar or microphone or whatever kind of
cable you're looking for, don't look any further than Hosea. They really are awesome cables. They
have different levels, good, better, best, and they're all very good actually. So let's talk
about connectors. The first connector I want to talk about is the quarter inch connector.
This would be also called an instrument cable or a guitar cable. Quarter inch, instrument,
guitar cable. These are all synonymous with each other. So if someone says, hey, hand me that guitar
cable or hand me that instrument cable. This is what they're talking about.
So the quarter inch cable just has two ends like this usually. And this is the male connector.
They're both male connectors. And we'll talk about that in a second. But they basically just one goes
in your guitar, one goes in your pedal board or amp. There's a bunch of different applications for
quarter inch cables. So this is what the quarter inch connector looks like. Now there is a male end and
the female end to just about any cable really. And this is the male end. And I'll let you decide
why it's called the male end. I'm not going to go into that, but let me see. Where was the
other one I was looking at? Oh, and then this is the female end there. And it's just basically
the male end goes into the female end. And so, you know, on your guitar, that's what this is going to be.
This is the female quarter inch connector or the jack. A lot of times people just say jack. If it's
attached to something, it's usually called a jack. Then you just plug it in like that. So in theory,
I could have the end of this cable could be a female connector and I could keep on connecting them
and just making a big long chain. So this is the quarter inch connectors, the male and female
quarter inch connectors. The next kind of cable is the XLR cable. And that is this right here.
Now, XLR technically is just the designation for the cable end itself. But usually when someone says
XLR cable, they're meaning give me a microphone cable or an audio cable with these connectors at
the end of it. So you can see here, this also has two ends to it. This is the female end because it's
got three holes there. And this is the male end. It's got three stems there and they connect together.
And you can make audio cables like this. Microphone cables connect together and loop like that,
which there's no purpose in that other than storing it maybe. But you can connect them,
daisy chaining them. And then on the back of your speaker or whatever, it's going to have one of these
ends that's going to plug into or your microphone. There's a lot of different uses for this on a mixing
desk. Most of the inputs are going to be XLR. If it's a pro mixing desk, sometimes you'll have quarter
inch on the mixing desk as well. Usually those are your main connectors. Also, XLR cables can be
data cables used for DMX lights. And we'll talk about that in just a minute. Right now, we're going
to talk about just the connectors themselves. The next connector that is not known as much on the lower
end stuff, but a lot higher end pro audio gear has speak on connectors. And this is a speak on
connector right there. And this is, I think these are both the male ends right here. Now you'll see
sometimes that there'll be a female end. This is what the female end looks like. And they click in
like that. Now the great thing about speak on connectors is they lock into place until you pull
this back and you undo it. So basically they just go in like this, you twist them, it locks into place,
and then you've got a very, very secure cable until you pull this back. So these are speak on connectors.
If you can use them for your speakers, these are great because you're not going to have anybody
tripping over a cable and it unplugs. So if you're a DJ, maybe you're a mobile church setting up in a
school where people are walking around a lot, it's not a permanent situation. If you have the choice for
speak on, they're, they're very, very good. A lot of times too, you'll hear the word new tricks.
Someone will say, Hey, give me a new tricks cable or that new tricks connector. It actually isn't a
new tricks cable or new tricks connector. New tricks is a brand name. So it's kind of like Kleenex.
So, you know, if someone says, give me a Kleenex, they really, they're just saying, give me a tissue,
but Kleenex is synonymous with that. So sometimes if someone says, give me a new tricks connector,
they really mean speak on. And a lot of times you'll have a quarter inch to speak on adapter used as
well. If your speaker cabinet only has speak on connectors, but you only have quarter inch cables,
the next kind of connector we're going to talk about is the RCA cable. Now this one has a lot
of different applications that you will see, not just in pro audio, but in home audio as well.
And this is what the, the RCA connector looks like there. And you know, you'll see this a lot of times
the back of like a stereo system. There's just a lot of applications. The, the consumer world has
really embraced the RCA connector. But it's also has a lot of purposes in pro audio and in sound.
For example, a lot of times if you're doing anything stereo, if you're coming from a computer
and you're hooking up into a mixing desk, a lot of times they'll have from your computer to a,
like one cable coming out of that, which we'll talk about in a second.
And then it's making a Y connection to the mixing desk left and right. A lot of times the other end
of these will say, we'll have like a red and a yellow. These are also used in video as well.
They're, they're pretty cool cable because they'll transmit a lot of different types of information,
but this is the, the RCA connector right here. So the connector itself is called RCA.
The next connector is a 3.5 millimeter connector or a eighth inch sometimes is what it's called.
It actually 3.5 is, is more accurate, but let me open this up here. You're probably very familiar
with this because this is the kind of connector that's going to be on your phone. So if you're,
you're plugging this in from an iPod or an iPhone into something else, this is going to be the connector.
So that, that little jack that's on everybody's phone, that is a, a 3.5 millimeter jack. Now I'm going to
actually grab my headphones here. This is actually the headphones to my phone right here. And you can
see on this one, there's actually three white lines there. That's because this has a microphone hooked up
into this. There's actually three different signals happening left, right, and then the microphone.
Usually though, in the, the pro audio world, you're going to see this connector right here, which is,
it's got two lines here. This is a stereo connector, which means there's a left and a right. So this,
this has a stereo connector. Now this is the same type of thing. You're going to see a male in like
this and a female in. Also, before I move on too far, this is a quarter inch cable with a stereo
connector there, a left and right. So this actually has two cables in here, two signals going through
this cable as well. And we'll talk about that a little bit more in a second. The next cable we're
going to talk about is MIDI. This is a MIDI cable here, and it's got two different ends like this
that have five pins. They look similar to an XLR, but they have five pins. This is a data cable. It's
going to transmit, uh, ones and zeros from a keyboard or an effects pedal, or there's a lot of applications.
This is definitely a pro audio cable here. So a lot of times in the back of, of, uh, of keyboards,
you'll see MIDI. Um, a lot of times keyboards are kind of moving away from MIDI and they're going to USB.
So a lot of your older keyboards are going to see MIDI instead of the USB. If you're hooking it up
like to a computer to record or something like that. So this is a MIDI cable and it produces or
transmits data. So now that we've talked about the different types of connectors in cables, let's talk
about the cable itself. So for example, let me compare a few different cables that I might have.
This is a guitar cable and this is a speaker cable. Both of these have quarter inch jacks here,
but they're made for two different reasons. Obviously this guitar cable, this generally when someone says
quarter inch cable, they're talking about an instrument cable. They're talking about this. This is for
instrument purposes, but this thicker cable here is for speaker purposes. Now here's the thing with this.
Sometimes you can take a instrument cable and hook it up to a speaker and it'll work, but
instrument cables are not made for speakers. Instrument cables are not rated. They're not made for
sending loud to a loud speaker spending, sending the audio to a loud speaker. So even though sometimes if
you hook up this cable to a speaker, it'll work, it's not going to be as good as audio and I think
that you might be able to damage your equipment if it's kept on for a long, long time. If you're just
testing something out, it'll be just fine. But if you're carrying a load on this, this cable is
probably going to get kind of hot and I just wouldn't do it. Now the other way around, if you take a
speaker cable and try to use this for guitar, it's not going to do anything bad and it's not going to do
anything good either. It's not going to be able to transfer the signal. It literally just won't go
through. So anyway, sometimes you'll see these two different connectors used for two different
purposes. So how do you know if it's a connector or not? Like this one here, this one looks just like
an instrument cable, but it's not. It's a speaker cable. So how do you know on the cable itself,
see if you can read that there. It'll say speaker cable. And this one says speaker gauge,
speaker cable, 16 gauge. And so on these, on the instrument cable, it's going to say
either instrument or guitar cable. I don't know if you can see that there or not, but it'll say
guitar cable on there. So, or instrument cable. So that's how you know. So whenever you, you,
if you have a lot of cables, you might want to just label them. That's what I do. A lot of times,
I'll just put a piece of tape on the end of it and I'll just put GTR or SPK or something like that.
So I know if that's a speaker cable or if it is in fact a instrument cable. The next kind of connector
is XLR. And these three can all be used for speaker. You can use a, a, a speak on XLR or quarter inch
cable. And here's the thing. There's really not much of a difference between these cables. If you're
hooking them up to a speaker, you're pretty much going to get the same audio. Matter of fact,
a speak on cable and a quarter inch cable, these are the same cables with just different connectors
at the end. Now the XLR cable is a balanced cable, but it's not really going to make a difference in
the sound that you have. If you have a buzz in your system, perhaps you might want to try to use
an XLR instead of another cable. But generally speaking, XLR, quarter inch, speak on,
they're all going to work really well for speakers, but they're three different connectors.
Just depending on the manufacturer, they may want to use only quarter inch or only XLR or only speak on.
A lot of, a lot of backs of speaker cabinets have all three of them on it. So just it's the same basic
thing. People ask sometimes, are you going to get a lesser quality audio if you use a adapter,
like one of these going from a quarter inch to the speak on? No, you're not. All that the speak on is
doing is just making that really secure connection. Now over time, probably it's going to wear better,
the speak on connector is, than a quarter inch connector, but it's going to give you the same
sound. Same thing with if you're converting anything. If you're, if you're having like,
going from an eighth inch to a quarter inch, it's the same sound. It's just the connector
transmitting the signal. If it's a quality connector, then it's going to have good sound coming to it.
Now let's talk about XLR cables, both data and audio cables. Okay. So if it's a longer XLR audio cable,
usually it's going to be labeled like this one, it says microphone cable. Sometimes you'll see them
where they're labeled, uh, just XLR or they'll just say audio cable. Let's see this one here.
This one just says balanced, uh, interconnected. This one is shorter. It says it's a five foot cable.
It's a, it's just says audio. And the reason why that is, is because a five foot cable is not going
to be very good for a microphone because you can't hold it for very long. You can't even stand and sing
with it. So XLR cables are the connectors, but one is data and one is microphone. What does that mean?
These have different homages. Basically they're going to produce different frequencies. And so
they're going to transmit frequencies better for the different applications. So a lot of times you can
actually take a XLR microphone cable and plug it into a DMX light, which is going to be a, it's
transmitting data, uh, ones and zeros digital signal, and it'll actually transmit it, but it won't do it
well, and it's going to have some interference and it's not going to be as reliable as a DMX cable.
Basically the DMX cable is better at transmitting the digital information. So unless you're just in
an absolute pinch, use a data cable to transmit DMX signals and don't use a microphone cable.
Here's the thing, data cables, the DMX cable will not go the other way around. You cannot use a DMX cable
for a microphone or any sort of audio. It just simply is incapable of transmitting that information.
It's not made for that. It's a digital cable. It's not an analog cable for those purposes. So you can try
to hook it up. It's just, you're never going to get sound out of it. It does, you can use the, the, the
microphone cable for digital, even though it's not recommended, but it will not go the other way around.
So therefore what I do is I always label my DMX cables. I just put a piece of tape on it and I
write DMX on it just so that there's no way in the pinch. You know, the thing is whenever you need a
new cable, you don't always have a lot of time. So you're just like grabbing a cable and you're trying
to hook it up. So I always make sure that it's super, super obvious of DMX cables so that I don't
accidentally grab the wrong one. Now, if you ever have any questions with it, it'll say on here, let's see,
this one says DMX cable, 24 gauge, 120 ohm. If you look here, let me see if it'll focus on that.
So it'll say DMX cable on the cable itself and on a microphone cable. It will either have nothing,
which is usually they have it now though, because DMX is so popular or it'll say a microphone cable,
or it might even say audio cable or instrument cable. But usually it says microphone if it is a
microphone cable. So you want to make sure that it does say audio or microphone on the XLR if you're
using it for an audio purpose. So with cables, as you can see, it's actually not super complicated.
There's only really a handful of connectors. There's more connectors out there, but these are the ones
that you're going to encounter most. If you're working in sound or you're working in as a musician,
you're going to see these connectors all the time. It's important that as a musician, you're familiar
with these because it's kind of the language that everyone is speaking. This is the information that
you're going to need to know as a musician. And so hopefully this was helpful to you. If it was,
please hit the thumbs up button, subscribe to my YouTube channel. If you didn't like this video,
just go ahead and hit the thumbs down button. I won't be offended. I am kind of surprised you stuck
around this long just to hit the thumbs down. But if you did, it's all good. Okay.
I make videos that help make musicians better musicians. So hopefully this helped you.
Anyway, Kinnis Russell out and I'll see you in another video.