Hey, what's happening guys? Yesterday we talked about this class AB amplifier with the TDA2030.
And today, as promised, we're going to build that circuit.
So, I've had this kit on my wish list for a while.
It's from ICStation.com and it's the TDA2030 amplifier kit.
And I would like to thank Dave for sending it out to us.
So, we're going to build it and have ourselves a nice TDA2030.
If we take a look here at the circuit board, you can see there are a few changes from the circuit that I drew yesterday.
They're using 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 capacitors.
And my circuit had what?
8.
Then there are also 4 ceramic capacitors.
So, that's like 13 total capacitors here.
Yeah.
So, that's a little different.
Also, only one diode.
Which is a little strange.
But, I think we'll make it work.
Alright.
Buckle up.
We're going to do this fast mode.
Now, come on.
Another time.
But, let's check on.
I don't care about Eolt.
Okay.
So, we want to do this fast mode.
And we're going to do it fast pharmacist.
Doing it fast.
And we're going to use the cam.
Today we're going to do it fast debate.
And what's it mean?
We're going to do this fast mode.
I do not want a seat.
Now, we know the about theünk Ho.
When I look imbalpsy for some any piece,
I want to aim for time at the gym.
So, we will carry you over the profession.
We're going to do this fast decibels.
That's super lumico.
We'll do it fast and see you guys.
And, and download the Cristo from all across,
and is the Fi.
Thank you.
Well, we're just about done.
The only thing left is this little power jack.
And, no.
I don't want to use it.
I don't like those jacks.
I don't have anything to use it with.
So, for our purposes today, I'm just going to cut some wire.
And, strip it.
And, we'll just hook it up with alligator clips.
Now, one thing.
I just realized.
These speaker terminals here for bare wire.
Oh, that's kind of ugly.
Well, that needs fixed.
Yeah.
I don't have any speakers that hook up like that.
So, before we can really test this out.
Good.
I need to get a hold of a couple of speakers of that ilk.
I will grab some tomorrow.
I think if I go up to my mom's house, there might be some old stereo speakers from when
I was a boy.
So, we can go check that out.
Okay.
Last soldering for this guy.
It took me about an hour to put this together.
Aren't you glad I condensed it?
Alright.
So, the piece de resistance.
There we go.
Nice.
So, let's smoke test it.
We'll hook it up to 12 volts.
And hopefully, the only thing that lights up is the LED.
I got that set for 6 volts.
Let me get in here and change it.
Voltage.
Boom, boom.
Zip.
And I got that set for 6 volts.
lights up is the LED. I got that set for 6 volts let me get in here and change it.
Voltage boom boom zip and power. Okay so our LED is lit sniff testing
nothing seems unreasonably hot
yeah I guess I soldered everything in the right direction then power that down
now I don't know if you could see it in the video because it went so fast but I
put thermal grease in between those TDA 2030s and the heat sinks get these on
eBay just put in thermal paste you get like 10 syringes for two dollars or
something ridiculous like that. Alright so anyway there's our amplifier that's all
we can do for tonight we will do the rest when I pick up a pair of speakers to test
it with and instead of just shoving some audio through it I think what we might do
is hook up this AD9833 digital synthesis chip and put some different frequencies through it
you know we hook that up to the Arduino and we can sweep it through some different frequencies
and we'll put it on a scope and look at the output. So if you guys want to see that
give me the old thumbs up feel free to comment share and don't forget to subscribe.
That's it I'm out peace except the Ravens
you