The FlySky FSIA6B receiver has three types of communication protocols, the classic PWM, and two serial protocols, PPM and IBIS.
When this receiver is connected to a flight controller, one of the two serial connections is always used.
The flight controllers have so-called UART serial ports, where one line is used to receive information from the radio,
and another line is used to send information from the controller to the radio.
The first is called the RX line, and the second is called the TX line, or telemetry.
The PPM connection is located in the first vertical slot of the receiver.
The upper pin is used to send the information to the controller, and the lower two to supply power to the receiver.
If we are going to use this protocol, it must be previously activated in the radio.
The RX line by IBIS protocol is in the horizontal slot on the right.
The rightmost pin is used to send information to the controller, and the other two pins are used to power the receiver.
The sending line is connected to some RX pin of the controller.
The TX line by IBIS protocol is in the horizontal slot on the left.
The rightmost pin is used to receive information from the controller, and must be connected to some TX pin of the controller.
The other two pins are used to power the sensors.
Since the controller is already powered, these power pins are not used.
In the following example, we send information to the controller through a RX line by the PPM protocol.
In addition, we receive information from the controller through a TX line by IBIS.
In the iNAB configurator, the communications for the UART ports are configured.
We use UART2 for the TX line, and UART3 for the RX line.
We see that the radio sends information of the channel to the controller.
In addition, we see that the radio receives information from some sensors of this controller.
And that is all.
Thank you.