This video is sponsored by Brilliant.org. More about them later.
Hi there everyone. Today we're going to be talking about Betaflight's angle mode.
And for those of you that fly both acro and angle mode, you'll know that Betaflight's acro mode is
fantastic. It's a joy to fly. It's very responsive, it's very precise, and it's very stable in the
air. And you might also know that Betaflight's angle mode is kind of none of those things.
It's pretty wobbly, it's kind of imprecise, and it's very slow in comparison to acro mode.
I noticed this while I was flying Tiny Whoops over Christmas, and I decided to put some time
into figuring out what was going on with Betaflight's angle mode. And I think I've worked it out,
and I'm excited to share that with you today. So in this video, we're going to be looking at
the problems with angle mode that Betaflight has currently, and some of the solutions that we can
implement to fix it. And at the end of the video, I'm going to be showing you how you can test those
fixes for yourself, and enjoy a sneak peek of what Betaflight angle mode might be like in the future.
It's a lot to cover in one video, so let's not waste any more time. Let's dive right into it.
If you fly Betaflight angle mode, I'd love to know how you think it compares to acro mode
and other firmwares like silverware. Please let me know what you think down in the comments.
The first problem I noticed was one of speed and responsiveness in angle mode compared to acro.
Let me show you some flight footage so you can see exactly what I mean.
To make the comparison, let's start by looking at some sharp stick inputs in acro mode.
And this is showing what Betaflight is capable of in terms of responsiveness.
You can see that the quad is snapping left and right instantly in response to my stick inputs,
and it's very precise as well. It's stopping dead at the end of each of the movements.
If I switch to angle mode now, you can see that the character is totally different.
The quad is much slower and much softer to respond, and a lot less precise.
Each of the moves takes a lot longer, and I'm moving the sticks just as fast on the radio,
it's just the quad is much slower to respond.
If we switch back to acro again, immediately that snappy response is back.
So there's a big gap in flight performance between acro and angle mode.
So why is Betaflight's angle mode so much slower and less responsive than acro mode?
Well, to explain, we're going to have to look in detail at how the Betaflight angle controller actually works.
In the blue line, we have the stick input from your controller, which is the requested angle of the quad.
And here it starts at centre, I move it over to the right hand side, and then back to centre again.
The green line shows the angle the quad is actually at.
And the way the angle mode controller works is it looks at the difference between the requested angle and the actual angle,
multiplies that by a factor, and that creates the gyro setpoint,
which tells the quad how fast to rotate towards the requested angle.
So you might be able to see the problem here.
Initially, we don't have much error between the requested angle and the actual angle of the quad.
So nothing much happens, the quad doesn't start to rotate.
Only once we have built up a lot of error,
is there enough push to get the quad to rotate quickly towards the new angle.
But things get worse because once my stick stops moving, the error starts to reduce again.
And so the quad slows down and takes a really long time to reach the requested angle.
This whole process takes hundreds of milliseconds.
It's about 10 times as long as the typical latency of a video or controlling.
So what can we do about angle mode being so slow?
Well, it turns out that Betaflight had already solved this problem in acro mode.
In acro mode, there's an extra term in the controller called feedforward that is designed to reduce this delay.
And the way feedforward works is it looks at the movement of your sticks, how fast you're moving your sticks,
and pushes the quad in that direction right away.
So let's take a look at what this chart looks like if we add feedforward in.
Here's the same chart with feedforward in the mix.
You can see that immediately as we move the sticks, there's a big strong push here from feedforward,
which gets the quad moving in the right direction right away before any error has built up.
Once the stick stops moving, that feedforward push stops as well.
But by that point, we have a lot less error and the quad is much closer to the requested angle than it was before.
And so the end of the move finishes off nice and quickly.
Overall, this is so much faster and more responsive than what we had without feedforward.
I found that adding feedforward into angle mode made the biggest difference for me personally
when flying tiny loops around indoors in tight spaces.
The reduction in effective latency of tens or even hundreds of milliseconds
from when you move the stick to when the quad responds in the air
just allows you to avoid obstacles so much more easily
and fly through tight gaps with a lot more precision.
I think the tiny races in particular are going to get a lot of value out of this new feature
and it's going to make them a lot faster around the track.
One of the challenges we faced with adding feedforward
is that it makes the quad very responsive to small stick inputs,
which can make the quad feel a bit jittery, a bit on edge.
Fortunately, Chris Thompson came up with a great fix for this,
which is feedforward smoothing.
So this spreads out the push of feedforward in time
and makes it less responsive to small stick inputs.
The result is that you can adjust the feedforward gain
to get the push you need to make the quad nice and responsive in angle mode.
And then separately, you can adjust the smoothing factor
so that it doesn't feel too jittery and on edge
in response to small stick inputs.
But that wasn't the only issue that I identified with angle mode.
The second issue is one of wobbliness.
So let's take a look at what makes angle mode so wobbly in comparison to Acro.
To show you what I mean,
here's some flight footage in angle mode
where I'm just making sharp your inputs.
I'm not doing anything else, just sharp your inputs.
And can you see how much the quad is wobbling around on pitch and roll as a result?
That's really counterproductive for flying precisely in tight spaces.
If you're enjoying this video so far,
please hit the like button to help other people find it on YouTube.
And if you haven't already, consider subscribing
so you don't miss out on future videos.
So what's going on here?
What's causing that really bad wobble on sharp your moves?
Well, I have here a little quad to show you what is happening.
So here we have the quad and I'm just going to be flying forward
so the quad is pitched forward like that,
but absolutely flat, just pitched forward.
Now I'm going to yaw the quad by 90 degrees.
Can you see that now the quad is no longer pitched forward at all?
It's rolled to the right.
That yaw move has converted the pitch that we used to have into roll.
Now, once that happens, the angle controller freaks out a bit and goes,
I shouldn't have any roll.
I should just have pitch.
And so it then tries to correct to get the quad back on track.
And that happens very slowly because it's all error-based
and it creates a big wobble after the move.
What's causing this problem and what can we do to fix it?
Well, the problem is being caused by the fact
we have two different coordinate systems at play here.
The first is the angle mode coordinate system,
which is earth referenced.
And that means that the roll and the pitch axes
are always level with the horizon
and yaw is vertically up and down.
We also have a control coordinate system,
which is quad referenced.
It moves with the quad.
So the yaw axis for the control of the quad
is always vertically up and down on the quad.
And when the quad pitches forward,
the yaw axis pitches forward.
Whenever these two coordinate systems are not aligned,
so whenever the quad coordinate system
is not aligned with the angle mode coordinate system,
we get error building up.
And that causes wobbles in the video feed that you see.
So how can we fix it?
Well, again, we have to think and look at acro mode.
When we're flying in acro mode,
we automatically coordinate a little bit of roll
in with our yaw turns to make sure
that the quad stays nice and level
through the yaw move.
And this is exactly the same thing
that we need to do in angle mode.
Unfortunately, it's a little bit more difficult
in angle mode.
To coordinate a turn,
we really need both the yaw and the roll sticks
to be rates of rotation.
And in angle mode, they're not.
The yaw stick is a rate of rotation,
but the roll stick is a requested angle.
So we can't really coordinate the turn in the same way.
Fortunately, we can write some code
into the angle controller
to coordinate the turn for us
so that when we do a pure yaw move,
the angle controller adds in
just the right amount of roll
for the quad to do a pure yaw move
in the earth reference coordinate system.
And when that happens,
we don't see any error build up on pitch or roll
during the fast yaw move.
And if there's no error, there's no wobble.
Let's look at some flight footage now
to see how that affects the behavior of the quad.
Here's some flight footage
where we're doing sharp yaw moves as before,
but the code in the angle controller
is coordinating the turn for us.
Sorry for the water on the lens.
That's an occupational hazard of flying in the UK.
We can see that the quad is much flatter
on those yaw turns
and it's not wobbling around
after the yaw move anywhere near as much.
One of the things that I really noticed
when flying this yaw coordination code
was how much less drift there was in the quad
and how much more precise it was at flying tight lines.
Before, when I was flying along
and I yawed sharply,
the quad would keep drifting
in the direction that it was going in
until the angle controller kind of sorted everything out
and got it flying in the right direction,
which took a few hundred milliseconds.
With the yaw coordination code,
when the quad's flying along
and you yaw,
there's no component of thrust
in the direction you were going in.
So the quad just flies straight forward
with a lot less sideways drift.
And that really does make it feel
a lot more precise in my opinion.
Now that we've talked through the problems
with angle mode
and how we've addressed them,
I want to show you
how you can test this code out for yourself
and put it on your Tiny Whoops
to fly around today.
Before we start testing any new code,
it's very important
that we fully back up our configuration.
So go into Betaflight Configurator,
go into the CLI
and type dump.
That will dump out your entire config
so that if you need to restore it later,
you've got everything that you need.
Make sure you save that to a file
in a place where you'll remember it
and call it something suitable.
I'm calling this AOS 3.5 dump.
Once you've got the dump,
clear your output history
and type diff.
That will give you the difference
between your configuration
and Betaflight defaults.
And save that to another file.
Call that one something memorable as well.
Once you've got those two files saved,
if you have any issues
and you want to go back
to your old configuration,
all you'll need to do
is to reflash the same version of Betaflight
that you currently have
and then just paste in your dump,
type save and hit enter.
And that will completely restore your config
to exactly what it is now.
That's really important
because you don't want to get into a situation
where stuff isn't working
and you can't get back
to a good working configuration.
So now that everything's backed up,
let's go and try out the test code.
Because this test code
is based on Betaflight 4.4,
you're going to need
at least version 10.9
of the configurator.
At the time of recording,
that isn't released yet.
So I'm going to be using
a nightly build
from this releases page
and I'll put a link to it
down in the video description.
If when you're looking at this video,
Betaflight Configurator 10.9
has been released,
you can just use the release build.
Once you have
Betaflight Configurator 10.9,
you're going to need
to get hold of the test code.
And the easiest way
is to go to the PR,
which is PR 12067.
There'll be a link
down in the video description.
Scroll down
and find the most recent
do you want to test this code?
Here you have
an automated build comment.
And inside there
is going to be
a bunch of assets
and you can download them.
Once you've downloaded
the assets zip folder,
you can just extract it.
And inside,
you'll find a whole bunch
of hex files.
And each of these
is for a different target
of Betaflight.
What you'll need to know
is exactly what chip
your flight controller has.
Does it have an F722?
In which case,
you'll use this F7X2 hex file.
If you've got an F405,
it will be the F405 hex file.
You get the idea.
You need to match
the exact chip.
So you need to know
more than just
is it an F4 or an F7.
You need to know
exactly what chip it is
and then pick
the right hex file
from this list.
Otherwise, it won't work.
When you know
exactly what hex file
you need,
you can jump into
Update Firmware
and then you're going
to want to select
your target.
So I'm just going
to hit Auto Detect
and it will find
the right target.
You can see
I've got an F745 here.
So I'm going to be using
the F745 hex file.
Load firmware
from your local drive
and in this test code,
you're going to select
the right hex file.
So for me,
that's F745
and then hit Flash Firmware.
If you have any problems
during the flashing stage,
I find the best thing
to try first
is ImpulseRC Driver Fixer
because most of the time
that's going to be
the cause of the problem.
I'll put a link
to that down in the video
description as well.
Once you've flashed
the firmware,
you can hit Connect
and you'll be asked
if you want to apply
custom defaults.
Always select Yes.
The flight controller
will reboot
and then you can hit
Connect again
and go back into the CLI.
Now we're going to paste
in the diff
that we saved before.
So we can load from file,
select the diff,
hit Execute
and all of that
will be executed.
You may get
some invalid names
depending on
whether you're updating
from a different version
of Betaflight.
It's not usually a problem.
You can type Save
and then hit Enter.
At this point,
it's a good idea
just to check through
your config
to make sure everything's
set up as you want it.
If everything looks good,
you can jump to the CLI
and type Get Angle
and you should see
Angle P Gain,
Angle Feed Forward,
Angle Feed Forward Smoothing
and Angle Earth Ref
as new settings
which you can adjust.
And for more information
on tuning,
I'll let you read
the full PR 12067
and that will tell you
what all of these terms do
and how you should go
about tuning them.
I hope that those
short instructions
give you what you need
to get started
trying out these new features.
If you're thinking
of playing around
with Betaflight test code,
you should definitely know
about the Betaflight Discord server.
I'll put a link to that
down in the video description.
It's a great place
to get help and support
if you need it
and also to leave
your comments
and feedback
on these new features
to help inform
the further development of them.
Now it's time
for a word
from our sponsor,
Brilliant.org.
If you're like me,
the FPV hobby
represents a fun
and exciting way
to apply maths,
science and engineering skills.
And whether you're
a young professional
looking to upskill
as you grow into your career
or you're someone
who just loves
finding new hobbies
and exploring new ideas,
Brilliant offers
thousands of classes
on maths,
science and computer science
with new ones
being added every single month.
If you're interested
in computer science
and maybe even looking forward
to contributing
to an open source project
like Betaflight
in the future,
then courses like this
on algorithm fundamentals
are a great place
to start building
the skills that you'll need.
To get started for free,
visit brilliant.org
slash ChrisRossa
or click the link
in the video description.
The first 200 people
to do so
will also get 20% off
an annual premium subscription
with Brilliant
so you can reach
your learning goals
and save a little bit
of money at the same time.
That's all I have
for you for today.
So until next time,
I wish you all
very, very happy flying.